Guide to the Papers of Nicholas Wahl MC 146
New York University Archives
Nicholas Wahl Papers
1944-1995
MC 146
New York University Archives
120.0 linear feet
The Papers of Nicholas Wahl document Wahl's contributions as a student, professor and academic administrator from 1949 to 1995. The majority of materials document his career as professor and director at New York University's Institute of French Studies from 1978 to 1996. Wahl's publications, speeches, research, course material, and correspondence reflect his lifetime study of French politics and society, in particular his expertise on former French President Charles De Gaulle.
Wahl, Nicholas
Scope and Contents
The Papers of Nicholas Wahl measure 120 linear feet and span the dates 1944 to 1995. Documents include newspaper clippings; reprinted articles, books and scholarly manuscripts (presented in conferences or for colleague review); political flyers, posters, campaign materials, and other materials related to French politics; colleague publications and student papers, mainly related to de Gaulle and the Fifth Republic; professional and personal correspondence; and personal notes, outlines, idea sheets, and other miscellaneous research materials for use in Wahl's dissertation, articles, book reviews, lectures, and speeches.
Series I: De Gaulle Materials and Related Materials
1944-1995, undated
The series is approximately 16 linear feet and consists of two subseries: De Gaulle Materials and Related Materials and Institut Charles de Gaulle. This series reflects Wahl's study of Gaullism, de Gaulle, and French politics, an interest that began with his graduate studies during the transition of the 4th into the 5th Republic and de Gaulle's return to power by 1958. Documents include publications, notes, political flyers, correspondence, and conference materials.
Subseries I: De Gaulle Materials and Related Materials
Boxes 1-12, Oversize boxes 1-7, Oversize Case 2, Drawer 14 1944-1995, undated This subseries measures approximately 14.5 linear feet and is arranged chronologically. Materials include Wahl's dissertation, notebooks containing Wahl's notes on his interviews with de Gaulle, additional research material, and correspondence related to his research.
Wahl's dissertation materials contain notes, drafts, and the final version of the dissertation, De Gaulle and the Resistance. Materials from Wahl's exclusive interviews with de Gaulle in Algeria consist of notebooks and notes as well as Algerian maps, brochures, and itineraries. Remaining materials consist of supporting documents related to de Gaulle, including flyers and brochures about his regime from election and referendum years (in particular 1958, 1965, 1968); French, and to a lesser extent American and British, newspapers and newspaper clippings, as well as other publications that discuss, review, and/or analyze political events; brochures and drafts of manuscripts from conferences; student papers; and Wahl's notes and ideas on de Gaulle, Gaullism and the Fifth Republic. Correspondence relating to de Gaulle is interspersed in this subseries instead of being placed in the Correspondence series. Correspondents include Wahl's coterie of fellow academics, political scientists, and politicians who sent him their comments on the Gaullist regime.
Examples of items contained in Series I, Subseries I:
"Oui Non" from the 1958 Referendum, [Numero special, Sep 1958](box 3, folder 8).
"Vous à Apporté," [Sep 1, 1965 - Supplement à "La Nation"] (box 4, folder 37).
Pamphlets from the 1958 Referendum, [Sep 1958] (box 3, folder 8).
Pamphlets from the 1958 Referendum, [Sep 1958] (box 3, folder 8).
Subseries II: Institut Charles de Gaulle
Boxes 13-14,
1969-1995, undated
This subseries consists of 1.5 linear feet and is organized chronologically by the date of the printed materials, conferences, and correspondence. Documents consist of reprints from conferences sponsored by this institute as well as correspondence from or addressed to the Institut. See www.charles-de-gaulle.org/ for descriptions of the Institut Charles de Gaulle.
Series II: Correspondence
Boxes 1-7
1954-1995 This series consists of 7 linear feet and is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's last name or organization/institution. The exception to this arrangement is when Wahl designated a specific subject title for a folder. In this instance, all materials have been kept in the folder and filed under that subject rather than being individually filed. These folders generally contain miscellaneous correspondence, often related to a specific time period (e.g., "Paris, April 86"). Correspondents include Benoit d'Aboville (Consul Général), Michel Guggenheim, Stanley Hoffman, François Mitterand, Antoine de Tarlé, and Michel Debré.
Series III: Political Party Information
Boxes 1-4
1945-1993, undated
This series measures 4 linear feet and is arranged chronologically under the categories of Elections, Political Parties and Political Publications. Elections that are documented include municipal and legislative elections held in Paris and La Sarthe between 1952 and 1986 and presidential elections held between 1965 and 1988. Materials consist of campaign flyers, pamphlets and ballots. The Political Parties category, filed under party names, includes both French and English political organizations such as Parti Socialiste S.F.I.O., Mouvement Républicain Populaire (M.R.P.), Club Jean Moulin, the Labour Party and the Conservative Party. Materials related to each group are filed under the sub-categories of Publications and Annual Conventions. The Political Publications category includes reports and reviews, journals and pamphlets on French politics from the 1950s to the early 1990s. A few publications cover English politics in the 1960s.
Example of items contained in Series III:
Political Buttons, [1970s] (box 4, folder 1).
Series IV: Miscellaneous Notes/Various Research (Partially Processed)
Box 1-4, additional unprocessed boxes
1947-1994, undated
This series is partially processed and arranged chronologically. Processed materials measure 4 linear feet. Documents include notes and research by Wahl and "idea sheets," on which he organized his ideas. Also included are newspaper clippings, which are arranged in folders labeled by research topic. Some newspaper clippings and publications relate to political party information (See Box 1, 1948, 1953 "miscel., fascists, travillistes," 1950-1952 "SFIO & Statutes," 1952-1953 "MRP & CFTC," 1952-1953, undated "PC," 1952-1954 "Miscel. Archival Materials," and 1953 "Independents, Peasants, ARS" and Box 3, undated "current scraps").
Series V: Conferences (Unprocessed)
Boxes 1-18
1940-1990, undated
This series has not been processed, but has been arranged chronologically by decade. Materials include conference schedules, reprints of conference papers and presentations, and conference notes. The majority of the conferences concerned France and/or French politics, but other topics are also present. Materials reflect Wahl's participation in conferences, including roles as organizer, consultant, participant, and attendee. Also included are materials from conferences he was unable to attend.
Series VI: Publications (Partially Processed)
Box 1-14
This series has been partically processed. Materials have been divided into two subseries: Wahl-related Publications and Other Publications. Wahl-related publications include materials related to articles, books and contributions to publications authored by Wahl, speeches delivered by Wahl, as well as publications and articles featuring Wahl. The majority of the non-Wahl related materials are reprints of publications, many of which contain dedications to Wahl by the authors.
Series VII: Associations (Unprocessed)
Includes materials related to institutes, organizations, and committees Wahl helped organize, served on or otherwise was involved including the European Studies Institute and the German Marshall Fund.
Series VIII: Course Materials (Unprocessed)
Contains administrative correspondence, syllabi, and other materials related to both courses Wahl took as a graduate student at Harvard and those he taught at Harvard, Princeton, and NYU, as well as other institutions at which he served as a visiting professor.
Arrangement
The collection consists of materials originally located in his IFS office at NYU. Order to the collection had to be established. In cases where Wahl organized his materials in labeled folders, their contents were kept together under the same title. These titles appear within quotation marks. Notes on the contents of the folder are listed underneath the title.
Series I, III, IV, V, VII, and VIII are arranged chronologically. Series II is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Series VI is arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
The collection has been organized into eight series:
De Gaulle Materials and Related Materials
Correspondence
Political Party Information
Miscellaneous Notes/Various Research (Partially Processed)
Conferences (Unprocessed)
Publications (Partially Processed)
Associations (Unprocessed)
Course Materials (Unprocessed)
Biography of Nicholas Wahl
Anthony Nicholas Maria Wahl, born June 7, 1928, to Hungarian immigrant parents, grew up in New York, New York. In 1949 Wahl earned his Bachelor of Arts in history from the University of Wisconsin, and in 1956 he earned his doctorate in political science from Harvard University. Wahl's dissertation, De Gaulle and the Resistance¸ which focused on the rivalry that developed in wartime between De Gaulle's Free French in exile and the resistance movement in France, brought him to the frontlines of French politics. During his studies he developed personal and professional connections to political scientists and various French politicians, such as Charles de Gaulle and Michel Debré, both of whom later gained political power in the late 1950s through the 1960s. Throughout his lifetime, Wahl maintained these advantageous personal and professional connections that he had fostered in his early education and career.
After completing his graduate work, Wahl became an instructor of undergraduate- and graduate-level history, government, and political science courses at Harvard University (1958-1964) and Princeton University (1964-1978). He also served as a visiting professor at various institutions including Columbia University, Nuffield College at Oxford, University of Paris X-Nanterre: Institut d'Etudes Politiques, the University of Saigon and Bryn Mawr College.
In 1978 Wahl was courted by New York University (NYU) to found the Institute of French Studies (IFS). While teaching French politics, history, and social sciences, Wahl also helped mold the institute into a thriving center for the interdisciplinary study of French society through social sciences. Regular visitations, lectures, and instruction by French politicians and academics helped to achieve one of the goals of the IFS: to foster dialogue between the United States and France.
Wahl rose to prominence in French and European studies circles through his participation in organizations, frequent contributions to publications, and regular attendance at conferences. He co-founded the Association for French Cultural Studies, and in 1975 he served as co-founder and first president of the French American Foundation. Wahl's efforts received recognition from his colleagues who often dedicated their own works to him. More notably, the French government awarded him the Chevalier of the National Order of the Legion of Honor.
On September 13, 1996, Wahl succumbed to cancer in London. His achievements as a scholar and contributions to the development of French cultural studies have created invaluable resources for continuing generations of students.
Sources:
Nicholas Wahl, Biographical File, New York University Archives, Archives H.
"In Memoriam Nicholas Wahl," French Politics and Society, Vol. 14, No. 4, Autumn 1996.
Access Restrictions
Series I to III are open for research, although some restrictions may apply.
Additionally, institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Please contact the University Archivists with specific questions regarding restrictions.
Provenance
The Papers of Nicholas Wahl were donated by the Institute of French Studies (IFS) of New York University (NYU) to the New York University Archives following Wahl's death in 1996.
Aboville, Antoine d'; Club Jean Moulin.; Debré, Michel, 1912-1996; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970; German Marshall Fund of the United States.; Guggenheim, Michel; Hoffmann, Stanley; Institut Charles de Gaulle.; Mitterand, François, 1916-; Mouvement républicain populaire.; New York University. Center for French Civilization and Culture.; New York University. Institute of French Studies.; Parti socialiste-S.F.I.O..; Rassemblement pour la République.; Tarlé, Antoine de; Wahl, Nicholas; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Culture |x Study and teaching.; Fliers (printed matter).; France |x Foreign relations |z United States.; France |x Politics and government |y 1945-1958 |x Congresses.; France |x Study and teaching.; France. |t Constitution (1958).; Journals (periodicals).; Magazines (periodicals).; Manuscripts for publication.; Newspapers.; Notes.; Posters.; Presidents |z France |x Election |x Congresses.; Research notes.; United States |x Foreign relations |z France.
- Series I: De Gaulle Materials and related materials
  - Subseries 1: De Gaulle Materials and Related Materials
    - De Gaulle Notebooks, 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rapport sur la Politique Economique d'Après - Guerre by René Courtin, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Publications: Ministre de l'Information, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "RPF const. Ideas", 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "RPF Status Reglements, Structure", 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Student Thesis: The Rassemblement du Peuple Français by Roy Pierce, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "De Gaulle speeches etc. May 1950 - Nov. 1953 discours de deG", 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Parl. Group", 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Lille 1952-1953", 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Cahier Team, Cahier Project", 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "RPF: Provisional Press, Federations, Groupes, etc.", 1952 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Old Outlines - original thesis project: pre-SSRC (Gaullist Workers Theme)", 1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Capitant Constit. Ideas", 1952, 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Miscel Archival Materials 52-53 57-58", 1952-1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "CED: Party Views Schuman Plan Europ Union", 1953 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Current Intro & Current Titles", 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "De Gaulle Book, Org., Titles, etc", 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Journée Nationale 'Assises' 1954 Dec." (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Old Trial Summaries", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - "Old Outlines", 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Courrier d'Information Dec. 1954 - Nov. 26, 1955", 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "De Gaulle speeches etc. 1954-1958" (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Reviews of de Gaulle Memoirs - Notes on Vol. III of war memoirs", 1954-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "De Gaulle Profile", 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Introduction - idea sheets", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "General Gaullist Constit. Ideas/RPF & Gaullist Constit Reform", 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Constitution Reform Ideas 1956 - May 1958, Presidentialism, etc", 1955-1959 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Ph.D. Dissertation Footnotes, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Ph.D. '56 original typescript" (folder 1 of 2), 1956 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Ph.D. '56 original typescript" (folder 2 of 2), 1956 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Publications, 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - voici pourquoi, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Notes, Newspaper Clippings, 1957-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "57-58 speeches on de Gaulle", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Nationalism (May '58)", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Appelons de Gaulle campaign April - May 1958" (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "De Gaulle return May - June 1958" (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Notes on the Algiers 'Coup' of May 1958" (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Association Nationale Duperier", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "58 const. Docs from Debré/Mamert", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Convention", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "'58 constitution analyses", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Allocution de Monsieur Delbecque en date du 16 Mai 1958 à Radio Algérie" (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "May Miscel. Press", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Referendum Yes Materials", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Propaganda: Referendum of 1958 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Union Civique, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Publications, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Miscel. Gaullist Salut Public etc.", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Propaganda: Elections in November '58, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Reprint on Bezzit, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "De Gaulle scraps on Algeria '58", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Algiers Press Kit", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Wahl's Visit to Algeria, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Reprints, Notes, Newspaper Clippings, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence and Publications, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Nuffield College Conference Dec. 1958" (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Conference: Conference de Presse du General de Gaulle, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Field Notes Etc.", 1958 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Field Notes '58-'59", 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Publications, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Current French Politics - Notes on Reading", 1958-1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Current de Gaulle res. Letters to Mme de Gaulle & Debré of condol. 70", 1958-1971 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "'58 - '64 Field Notes" (folder 1 of 3), 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "'58 - '64 Field Notes: France Summer 1960, De Gaulle Plus 5th Republique" (folder 2 of 3), 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "'58 - '64 Field Notes: Paris Notes June - July 1964 on de Gaulle only" (folder 3 of 3), 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Notes, Manuscripts, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Interviews with de Gaulle and Debré, 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - "Debré Constit Ideas", 1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - The French Constitution of 1958: II The Initial Draft and its Origins by Nicholas Wahl, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - "APSA Draft", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - "APSA Paper September '59", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - "De Gaulle & France", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - "Revue Française Française de Science Politique Article & APSA '59 Article", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Lecture Notes, Mimeograph for Class, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - "Debré government - 1959" (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - "Chapt. II De Gaulle sens du réel materials milit. Doct. Materials", 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Reprints, 1959-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - De Gaulle's Visit to the U.S. President, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "De Gaulle Significance in French Political Tradition -CIA Seminar Oct 1960 De Gaulle (1)Aron (2)NW;Pol. Change in France;Keys to de Gaulle - Erikson, Columbia '60 etc", 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Publications, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes, Correspondence, 1960, 1963, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Erikson", 1960, 1961, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Esprit, 1960-1968 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Congrès de L'ONR Discours de M. Michel Debré, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - De Gaulle: Ideas, Politics, Effects by Stanley Hoffmann, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, Manuscript, Notes, 1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Notes, Newspaper Clippings, 1961, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Notes: De Gaulle Press Conference, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Touchard Gaullism Seminar Science Politique '62-'63", 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "NW personal mail", 1962, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - "Origins of the RPF - Sciences Po June 1963" (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Brochure: U.N.R. and U.D.T., 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Notes, Drafts, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "De Gaulle - 20's & 30's writings - Notes", 1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - "RPF Cahier Sciences Politiques Seminar Gaullism", 1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Nouvelle Frontière, 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Reprints, 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Manuscript: Le Gaullisme, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - L'Esprit Publique: De Gaulle Démosqué, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Notes, Newspaper Clippings, 1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - "Pantheonisation" by Jean Moulin, 1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "Main Themes", 1964, 1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - "Research Support, Travel Support", 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Publications, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence: Andrews, William, 1964-1969 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Publications, 1964-1970 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1958-1965 Des Faits Des Chiffres: 7 ans de vieme (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - "Erikson notes plus basic biographical research", 1963-1965 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence: Larmour, Peter, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Elections: Publications, Propaganda, Newspaper Clippings, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Propaganda: U.N.R., U.D.T. and Christian Organizations, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Discours Prononcé au Palais des Sports, le 15 décembre 1965 par Monsieur André Malraux au Nom de l'Association, 'Pour la Vème République' (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - French Politics Before the Presidential Battle by Serge Hurtig, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Propaganda, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - "Nov. 14 1965 speech Washington; April 1966 de Gaulle & NATO De Gaulle & Nato/Atlantic Community May '67 Foreign Policy Association - France Today", 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - "Field Notes", 1965, 1968, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Manuscript: The Popularity of Charles de Gaulle: Findings from Archive-based Research, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - "Foreign Policy Association", 1966 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Review: The Three Lives of Charles de Gaulle by David Schoenbrun, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Pictures, Brochures, Articles, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - "NW Reviews", 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - "Miscel. notes for filing", 1966-1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "De Gaulle's nationalism - miscel. notes, Princeton lectures", 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript: "Mains Libres" et "Vaste Plan": La Liberte d'Action Comme Clef de la Politique Extérieure Gaulliste, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Agnew de Gaulle res. '67 Chateaubriand Tukhachevsky", 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Today In France, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Students & Youth 67-68", 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Debré: Correspondence, Notes, Drafts, 1967, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - "1967-1969 Misc. Field Notes" (folder 1 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - "1967-1969 Misc. Field Notes" (folder 2 of 2) (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Publications, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "De Gaulle clips (Schick letters)", 1967-1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)